Okay. So my question is about duka
contemplation. Um so like I encounter
that that um like if um there is not
enough faith
uh then this do a contemplation can kind
of cause depression sort of because um
like when you um consider that like um I
mean death is inevitable suffering is
inevitable and you don't know that there
is a way out of it. So maybe like even
your practice is is also futile. Mhm.
>> So and basically then what you are kind
of you are just stuck in suffering
>> and yeah so how to deal with this? So
>> well I think see um the first question
would be like
why would you be contemplating duka in
the first place? What's your motivation
behind? Mhm.
Mhm.
>> Well, as far as I understand, it's a um
I mean I think it kind of makes you
sober about life and
>> No, but I mean specifically you like
when you contemplate duka, what's why
are you doing it? What do you expect to
come from that contemplation as a
practice? >> Um I would say I expect like some
>> Um I would say I expect like some
calmness and and dispassion to come from
it. >> But as often instead of this, it's
>> But as often instead of this, it's
coming a kind of some kind of despair or
sort of Yeah. Well, see, I think that's
already pretty much where the answer is. You're
pretty much where the answer is. You're
doing it to get something from it.
>> So, you want to contemplate it to get
the calmness, to get the dispassion,
but really you want to contemplate it so
to understand it on its own terms.
Even if no calmness comes, if no
dispassion come, which by the way, it's
impossible for it to not come. But if
your motivating factor is I want these
things to come that's why I contemplate
this that can kind of take the center
stage too much.
>> So although theoretically yes you
contemplate it so to be dispassionate
>> but on the immediate level
your your your immediate motivation can
be the reason why you're not getting
what you're what you're expecting to
get. Mhm.
>> In other words, the craving because of
which you're contemplating that is
maintained because you're overlooking it
and feeling justified in craving further
of this contemplation until the peace
and dispassion come.
>> Mhm.
>> So you are kind of blocking yourself so
to speak. Mhm.
>> But I I say in my case it's it's even
not quite like this because it seems
like these contemplations running in my
head on their own like uh to
>> I know it's like almost automatically
because uh I noticed that in past for
instance these things help me to
overcome like attachment to many things
like to see for that that work is not
really like so much important that I
know that like any like uh sexual stuff
is not important. and whatever else and
these things kind of running on their
own >> and it seems like at some point they
>> and it seems like at some point they
start
>> like devouring also the the youth that
practices >> is
>> is
well that's again like even back then
all of those contemplations were
infected with a craving with a desire of
wanting to get something from it
>> and it can work relatively speaking to
some extent
like uh that craving can help you place
you know craving for family,
partnership, work, career to crave for
forest, meditation and so on but it's
still craving. So the sooner or later
the time will come when that will be the
the the impediment the obstacle and um
given that yes you already have no
desire for career or work or academic
pursuits or family or partnerships. What
you're left with now is yeah that
craving that has helped you overcome
those say worldly attachments coarser
attachments now it's just too coarse to
address the subtler attachments and
what's too coarse it's that very craving
that motivates those expectations on a
kind of uh contemplation I expect peace
and dispassion but it's not coming it's
just depression and despair
because craving keeps that that as I
said polluted
>> so you really want to like recalibrate
it pretty much the context and the
reasons for contemplating things in the
first place and whereby hold on would I
be fine if for the rest of my life I
don't experience any peace nor any
dispassion why is that a problem for me
I still know what to do and what not to
do it still doesn't affect my choice to
keep the precepts and choose wisely even
if I don't get any reward for it so you
want to present that idea and see
whether your mind will be like whoa whoa
not the chance and it's like, well, why
not? Cuz it could happen.
Maybe you lose your health or something
and you won't be able to practice all
these things that you deem practice to
be. But internally, theoretically, you
But internally, theoretically, you
shouldn't be affected by that. If you're
practicing rightly, you shouldn't be
affected by that. So, that's what you
want to start showing to your own mind
that well, the time will come when we
won't be able to manage or do anything.
Will you be fine with that? And that's
what I mean like you want to kind of
refine your own motivation for practice
whereby no I contemplate duka so to
understand it and so that my mind gets
used to it that there is no resistance
or depression in face of it
>> that's a reward in and of itself but as
of now that reward is too subtle to be
measured by the expectation of reward of
peace and dispassion and that's why it
feels insignificant.
But so then what should one kind of um
I know tell to the mind tell to oneself
that that um um
that it stops expecting this kind of
like I know it's basically saying okay
like you you are doing this you're
keeping precepts or you are uh doing
your meditation contemplation or
whatever else And but you still you feel
like you're still afraid of of
suffering, still afraid of of death of
like I mean let's say uh on on like
sometimes mind presents some like
violent scenarios which are kind of yeah
frightening and uh and you see like I
know what to do with this. Yeah. So
>> well again for as long as see the mind
can only go so far
if your views don't support me expect
mind's expectations.
>> So um it feels as if oh well my mind
still expects or my mind fears or my
mind does this I must address it. But
all of that is enabled by your views
>> by what you still emphasize or deem
important. >> Mhm. So if you start rewriting your
>> Mhm. So if you start rewriting your
views i.e. correcting them then the mind
can't go that far
>> and eventually it will have to start to
follow because the views direct they set
up the direction.
>> So if your mind is still expecting still
this means you yourself is a good chance
are also still expecting it on account
of the views of the practice and what's
important and what should come from it.
you haven't questioned that long enough.
Like, and by the way, like maybe part of
your views might be quite okay, quite
right, but the fact that they were never
questioned, never brought to question
and into uncertainty for a sufficient
amount of time, they're wrong for that
reason. >> That's why like even the right view,
>> That's why like even the right view,
people can be holding it wrongly, which
is why it won't be their right view.
So, you yourself have to be
re-evaluating yourself. It's like okay
but am I also expecting things and then
contemplate enough to show you until it
sinks in that those things shouldn't be
expected because they make no sense and
then even if the mind comes up with
expectations it's contained within the
right perception that you developed with
with more correct views.
So ask yourself, as I said, um
would you be fine
with uncomfortable things, not being
able to practice or be on a retreat or
be in a seclusion or be sheltered from
stuff if you end up in environment where
those things are not accessible?
>> Now in your imagination, is that
affecting you?
>> Mhm.
>> And if it is, you realize, well, that's
really the root of the problem.
>> Mhm.
And that's already the first step to a
solution. Not just taking for granted
that yeah I must follow this through
whereby I will get that environment to
get that practice and never address the
fact that it bothers me.
>> And if I figure out that I'm bothered by
it so what's the
>> well that's see you figure out that
you're bothered by it and you recognize
okay this is what needs to be addressed.
>> Yes. Yes. So how
>> and whenever the pressure comes up to
follow that which bothers you as in like
to avoid it to go away it's like well
actually no that would be fueling it. M
>> so that's how you can as I said find a
good enough balance in terms of
environment >> where you wouldn't be too precious or
>> where you wouldn't be too precious or
too like high maintenance so to speak
and uh well the first step of when you
find that you're bother is to not act
out of the bother
that's how the views that revolve around
management of the border avoiding the
border uh finding the perfect
environment where nothing will bother
you those views will then evaporate
>> cuz again for maintenance of the views.
Um the whole kind of well the views
would pretty much depend on on mind
jumping on things left and right uh
management this avoidance resistance
mind jumping left and right management
resistance depends on you enabling it
through your actions.
>> So if you start not following through
with your actions the mind will have to
come down. Mhm.
>> If the mind comes down, the views would
have to settle down.
>> They can't remain. The cloud of dust
can't remain if there is nothing running
or up and down the road anymore.
>> So it's not like instantaneously kind of
unplugging something,
>> but it is like removing the supporting
factor until it settles down.
until it settles down.
So that's that's always say like it kind
of boils down to recognizing the
motivation >> for whatever aspect of the practice you
>> for whatever aspect of the practice you
you think you're developing or you want
to be developing and then not taking
that motivation for granted either but
recognizing hold on is this rooted in
avoidance. >> Is this rooted in fear? like am I
>> Is this rooted in fear? like am I
addressing fear or I'm just trying to
not deal with it
>> and and start like bringing it back home
basically where you kind of know I
should not be I should be able to not be
moved by this
>> even if my mind moves I'm the one who
should be able to not just act out and
follow through
with these pressures and compulsions and
so
So then I'd say like the [clears throat]
um the
start here is to to to kind of stop
trying to find some like perfect
alignment for for practice and whatever.
>> 100%. So
>> 100%. And like the sooner you stop that,
the sooner you begin the practice,
>> the practice that really matters towards
actual liability to suffer and
everything else regardless of the
circumstances. Mhm.
>> Um because the very kind of the nature
of say consciously choosing to not
follow the compulsion to manage or
address the discomfort that arises. It's
going to feel like like a like a very
strong confinement.
>> And that's why people don't do it.
That's why they justified trying like
changing and going further and doing
this and doing that and moving from here
to there because if they stop
>> it feels like you're enclosed completely
like like no no no escape
>> and that's unpleasant and that's the
beginning of practice.
So that's why again the precepts and
everything is just to train the mind to
enable you to be able to contain your
mind when it faces that confinement
and that confinement will come as the
Buddha described the four mountains
coming closer with every day. It's
nothing other than the confinement until
you're confined so much that you're
destroyed. Sickness, aging, death are the
Sickness, aging, death are the
unavoidable confinements. But the whole
practice is to create the confinement of
the right kind
so that the mind learns how to settle
within not to depend on action
and management in order for its
perception of its survival.
So in other words, you want to do it
before you want to train your mind in
regards to confinement before the
confinement really comes.
Um but yes, psychologically it will feel
the same. Like for many people just
having to take on the precepts will feel
like death, dying, fear, abyss as the
sutas described.
>> Mhm.
>> Cuz sensuality is that freedom. Saying
no to that feels like I mean like you're
buried into the ground alive and that's
that's frightening but only from the
point of view of depending on the
senses. So you might not have say you
might have refined that. So you don't
depend on the senses as much because
you've been restrained living in the
right environments and so on but you
might well be managing depending on
management on technique or or or counter
action when this happens and that or
movement within
and that's also a way of escaping
confinement and that's what the Buddha said like in
and that's what the Buddha said like in
the sutras says you have someone and
brahins that do take on restraint and be
start living withdrawn from sensuality
but then they hold on to the views and
start arguing and falling falling out
over views.
People often think that it's like uh
philosophical debates that they disagree
with. Oh, the world is eternal. No, the
world is not eternal. Well, you sir
don't know what you talk about and stuff
like no views literally means
standpoints in regard to day-to-day life
will become supercharged with importance
once you withdraw yourself from
sensuality. views that range and everybody that
views that range and everybody that
lived in the monastery saw that that
range from sure is the world eternal or
not to the point of how did you put your
shoes when you came in here in this
monastery we don't do that and it's like
it's really important because
confinement has come now because you are
not spilling out into the senses. So
you're going to have different ways
internally of compensating for that
fear. So these little things that other
people do become very very important and
must be aligned rightly because
otherwise I feel confined and if I don't
give in the first wave of compulsion to
to to to break out of that internal
mental confinement of my chitta then I
will give into the second wave or the
third wave because they're going to
become more and more increasingly
pressuring and irrational.
>> And that was the example many of us
seen. It's like, you know, the sutas
clearly say you shouldn't say anything
if it's rooted in irritation or anger
until your mind is in the right place,
until you recognize that it's beneficial
for everybody. And you would see that
like something would come up in the
community and you could see the monk is
like super irritated, annoyed,
threatened by it even. And they might
not say anything that immediate
occasion, but the next occasion they
would have to say something because in
their mind it's like the proliferation
increases. So, oh, if I don't say like
this, he'll do it again.
They don't stop and question, well, what
if they do it for the rest of their
life? What if everybody does the wrong
thing for the rest of their life? Can I
endure that confinement of not getting
my way? And it's like they don't go that
far. It's like I might not say it the
first day, but then I'll think, "Oh, but
he'll do it again." But then if he does
it, then he'll do it as well. Then
she'll do it. Then everybody will do it.
Then everything I worked for, the
monastery I built, the tradition we
present, all of it will go to ruin.
Therefore, I have to say it for the sake
of the dharma, for the sake of the
monastery, for I have to say it. So they
then prioritize
proliferated ideas of external
importance and circumstances and ignore
their own very intention that they're
still annoyed and that's why they're
saying it.
And like you say no once to your mind.
You might feel a bit of like a
resistance but it won't become
increasingly intensely irrational
immediately because again there is still
hope that eventually you'll say it and
the mind will get its way. But if you
don't say it again and again and again
the confinement the perception of
confinement is increasing and the animal
is going to start complaining. It's
going to be quicker to be agitated more
irrational more pressuring more
threatening. And that's exactly the
point. That's part of the practice. But
once that starts happening, that's where
people start to justify spilling out. So
they might not spill out as much as go
back to the sensuality, but it will
certainly spill out to the point of
arguing, carrying grudges, ill will on
account of views and disagreements and
how things should be and how things
should run and what you said and what he
meant and so on. And all of those views
on account of which summoners and
brahmins um stab each other with verbal
daggers as the sutas describe. and then
realize, oh yeah, okay, so I shouldn't
do that either. So I have withdraw
myself from sensuality, but now I have
to withdraw myself from these
standpoints. How do I do that? Well, by
questioning them for myself.
How is that going to feel? Well, exactly
how it felt before. It's going to feel
like your mind is now even more confined
because you're not allowing it. Quick
escape, quick management, quick cover
up, quick kind of addressing of things
so that everything feel fine. Feels
fine. And and that's that's actually a natural
And and that's that's actually a natural
progression. And that's why I said like
you choose to restrain today and then in
five days time there's still the same
pressure to say something comes up and
you still restrain
>> and then you restrain to the point of
there is no expiry date to this. If the
mind keeps coming up for the rest of my
life with this ridiculous irrational
compulsion pressure for the rest of my
life I will not intentionally allow it.
and enemy mind will get really really
upset with you
>> because now we're talking about kind of
ultimate scenarios. You're taking away
the hope that sooner or later you will
give in like how you used to do but you
don't. And by the way, it's it doesn't
need to be this these kind of grandiose
determinations of I will never lay down
or I shall never speak. Just these
little things when the I don't know the
eyes want to look the mouth wants to say
something you recognize it's unh
wholesome you don't do it and then it
comes up again and again and three
months later the same thing keeps coming
up you don't know it might be three days
it might be three months it might be
three years because you don't know how
deep the tendencies of cheetah go you
are ready to train the animal and if you
are ready to train the animal it doesn't
matter to you how long you have to train
it would be Nice. Sure, if it's not too
long, but doesn't matter. You're not
concerned with the length. You're
concerned with the quality of each and
every session, so to speak.
And what preferences your cheetah have?
Well, that can and how deep they go.
Well, that can only become apparent as
you start training it, right?
Cuz sometimes people would think, well,
surely two months later, I shouldn't be
thinking about the same pressure. It was
like, why not?
Are you thinking it? Are you choosing to
think it? Well, no, not really. So why
do you then expect to not be thinking
about it? Is that also up to you to
decide? Like no. So if for two years
later my mind is pressuring me with same
stuff, that's fine. I was never the
practice was never about changing what
mind thinks about. The practice was not
crossing the line when those things want
to push you over.
And if the mind what the mind thinks
about are not the things they want to
cross the line in terms of unbeneficial
behavior, that's fine.
And that's how you also recognize kind
of where your uh responsibility is.
So not spilling into sensuality, not
spilling into course act by body and
speech and then yeah not finding the
escape from that confinement in views
and standpoints and ideas of how things
should be and so on and so forth.
And when the mind does come up with
those expectations, you recognize the
same. I have to endure this now and not
fuel it and not take it for granted and
okay yeah yeah yeah let's find a
solution let's sort it out no hold on
why is it a problem
why does anything
like anything that mind comes up with
why do I have to do anything about it
anything about it why do I have to move
why do I have to figure it out why do I
why like why can't I just not do
[snorts] anything
and then you choose to do not do
anything and then the mind becomes even
more threatening. Not always but it can
happen. And it's like okay well surely that's
And it's like okay well surely that's
the problem not my doing or not doing of
practice. It's the fact that if the mind
is not getting what it wants when it
wants it, it turns it's turning against
me. It's pressuring me. It's threatening
me. I'm the one like, oh, it's like,
well, that's that's not a beneficial
arrangement
that the mind pressures you into
decisions, into action that you choose
to give in because the pressure is too
much.
But when when like the doubt comes then
like actually mind starts saying like
basically is there kind of you started
this because you thought that this can
help you to to overcome suffering
>> like you could say this is this was
craving >> but the mind starts saying okay you you
>> but the mind starts saying okay you you
are going this way maybe like I don't
know 10 years or whatever how many years
and and you're still kind of like
Uh you
>> well I mean yeah that's that's a valid
thing. >> Yeah
>> Yeah
>> that's a valid thing for a man to say.
>> Yes
>> because you should expect results.
>> Yes. Yes. And then you kind of say maybe
this like maybe it doesn't work. Maybe
you >> or maybe you've been doing it wrong.
>> or maybe you've been doing it wrong.
>> Maybe I've been wrong. Exactly. Like
like you start thinking like maybe I'm
incapable of this. Maybe it's just
wrong. or maybe like
>> so there is a difference between like
questioning it
>> um to an objective degree like well yeah
I've been doing this for 10 years and
you know
>> do you have anything to show for
>> but then there is a there is a
difference between that and when you
cross that line and go into well maybe
you are just hopeless maybe you you
don't know what you're doing maybe it's
like look the possibility for
enlightenment remains unddeinished for
as long as you're alive
>> even even This is questionable you know
it's like
>> well no it's not possibility is
something like it is possible that you
can that you can free yourself from
suffering >> but sometimes minds doubt mind
>> but sometimes minds doubt mind
>> well of course of course but that's
that's see like to a degree you have to
doubt things including your own practice
but when you recognize the doubt now to
be revolving around like a compulsive
core that's when you have to endure it
instead >> and that's the difference between like
>> and that's the difference between like
The doubt is a hindrance and the overall
doubt in like what freedom from
suffering is
because doubt is a hindrance is a habit
of the mind to pressure you to clarify
things that are uncertain.
>> That's something you actually have to
not give into and and and habitually
fuel it for the solution.
>> So if the mind starts doubting, oh well
is it even possible? It's like okay
that's a valid question but you stop
there. Mhm.
>> Is it even possible? Yeah, I don't know.
But I hope it is.
>> Mhm.
>> But that certainly doesn't allow you to
Oh, yeah. You're worthless. Well, where
did that come from? How do you know that
that that's the case? You don't.
>> So, you might think like, oh, I'm
nowhere near close to enlight closer to
enlightenment, but how do you know that
you are further away from it? You don't
know that either.
So you recognize the objective
uncertainty about it. But you have to be
careful as to how much you allow it that
compulsion to be fed through your own
seeking for the solution because
basically when the doubt is is comes up
as a hindrance like repetitively uh in
that compulsive sense it's not really
about the answer. It's about getting rid
of the discomfort of that experience.
>> So you're seeking the answer seemingly
to clarify the doubt. In reality, you're
seeking the answer so that the mind can
escape the confinement of this
uncomfortable feeling. That's it.
>> So if you don't forget that doubt is
unpleasant >> and then make the effort to not act out
>> and then make the effort to not act out
of that displeasure, you are containing
the doubt
and the more you do it like as like the
more irrational it will become and the
more irrational it become it it will
show you more and more how ridiculous
the mind is. Mhm.
>> But it was the power of compassion that
would always get you back in
>> and then become concerned with A's and
B's and C's as the answers and all this.
But in reality was always remaining the
same. Confinement of discomfort, [gasps]
can't bear it, act out and then spend
days and days trying to resolve
something until the feeling is appeased.
And that's basically inadvertently
fueling the doubt that you're trying to
resolve.
So if sometimes that doubt can have as I
said a legitimate basis such as well
I've been doing this for 10 years. Am I
free from suffering? No. Well that's a
valid reflection. But now when the
compulsion of that discomfort
see recognizing that oh maybe I'm I was
wrong is unpleasant. And now the doubt
comes on top of that amplifies that
discomfort. Do you stay with it and not fuel that
Do you stay with it and not fuel that
kind of mental proliferation? I kind of
doubt or do you think I must find a
solution while in reality you really
just trying to avoid that very
discomfort.
No, I think I I would like to find
solution but it feels like there's no
solution indeed because I know for like
this is there liberation or not I cannot
tell because I even if somebody told me
I'm he's an Ara I wouldn't know this
because >> well of course yeah this wouldn't like
>> well of course yeah this wouldn't like
even helping I mean
>> well you you don't need to I mean
obviously you can't know that there is
liberation unless you're on path to be
liberated yourself. So, but then my
point is if you feel like you're losing
faith, well, my point is that you also
can't not well you can't know that there
is no liberation either.
>> It's on the equal footing.
>> So whether you want it or not, you are
left in the state of liberation could be
possible >> and you have nothing to lose by trying.
>> and you have nothing to lose by trying.
because your life is objectively better
by not pursuing career, family, worldly
craving, money, uh partnerships,
relationship, entanglement, burden and
so on. So you realize, okay,
I I have a crisis of faith. I don't know
if it's possible, but I also don't know
if it's not possible either, which means
I might as well continue doing what I
can have and intelligent recognition is
beneficial for me and carries the
possibility of actually freeing me from
suffering. But at the same time, yes,
you obviously need to
develop some shift or some upgrade if
it's been 10 or more years and you're
still not free from suffering.
Not just uh indefinitely, well, it will
come when it comes. No, no, no. Surely
in 10 years time if things were being
done done rightly it should have come
like that it should have been developed
and now that's the unpleasant part.
You you feel like you might have to
start all over again or you might have
to undo what you thought you built and
that's where the doubt comes in. But
instead of taking it on
and not losing perspective, people then
want to manage the doubt one way or the
other to avoid the discomfort that it
revealed.
But the good thing is like if you start
practicing rightly you don't have to
wait for 10 years to get the results.
So even if somebody say wasted 50 years
of not getting anywhere not getting
anything from the practice
if then they start rightly
they can get it right.
So from that point of view, nothing's
been wasted. Even the wrong effort, so
to speak, in hindsight, can all be made
right if things are actually then done
rightly.
But until then,
a person has to stop
running away from confinement, internal
confinement.
And that happens all the time. Like in
most of the monasteries I remember it
was like uh monks are constantly moving
from one place to the other. when things
become like
too close to confining to this to that
go to the next place go and find another
aent go and find another one go and find
another one go and find another one and
then I met marks doing that for like 12
13 years 15 years and eventually you get
tired you can't be constantly moving or
trying to outrun the confinement and
then the only other option was left
dismissed the whole thing and then disro
basically or I stopped practicing
and uh Again,
all of that is the same attitude
that's been maintained from the day one.
When things got too confining,
I gave in and allow the mind to run away
through doing this or that and going
there and uh justifying
um management and so on.
Like you might kind of have to if it's
too much, but you don't need to lie to
yourself about it.
You don't need to justify it. Like, oh,
it's too much. This monastery is just
too much. I can't bear it here. It's too
strict. It's too this. It's too that.
The mind is overwhelming me. I need to
change. I want to go somewhere else when
it's a bit easier.
Like a person might do that, but they
can still do it authentically, so to
speak. They can recognize, okay, I'm not
ready for this level of confinement, so
I lower it down a bit. But there is no
need to lie to yourself and present that
as a some sort of practice and say, "Oh,
you can't practice here. Nobody knows
what they're doing here." Even if they
were true, none of that should be your
personal problem.
>> But people use that finding faults and
stuff so to justify them running out of
the confinement that their mind started
perceiving until the novelty of the new place runs
until the novelty of the new place runs
out and it starts to feel stale and
confining again. And and then I got to
find a new place and a new place and a
new place.
And ironically enough, then people
become monks become even more sensitive
monks become even more sensitive
and disturbed more easily disturbed by
sight smell touches than they were
before. Because the more you're trying to outrun
Because the more you're trying to outrun
the confinement, the bigger it gets,
>> which means the faster you need to run,
which means the quicker you'll be
reminded of the stuff that you're trying
to outrun.
Oh, they speak too loudly here. Oh, the
smell here is too bad. Oh, the food is
like this. Oh, it's too many people. Oh,
it's too little people. Oh, it's too
high. It's too low. It's too wet. It's
too dry. It's always going to be
something. And if you don't look past that and see
And if you don't look past that and see
where is my intention rooted in wanting
to do this or that move or say and it's
like oh well it's obviously rooted in
compulsion in pressure in mind trying to
get me to to release it back into the
wilderness to some extent to ease to
allow it some sort of uh relief it's
like oh that's the problem and wherever
I go I'll carry that problem I'll carry
that attitude
>> so no place will be perfect like can
live with 100 arons Buddha himself and
that person would still find fault with
it because all of that's done just to
compensate the responsibility for the
confinement and there was that whole
like a cha that funny story of uh monks
go around the monastery whichever
monastery they're in they complain about
it and he said it's like um going around
from a place to place carrying in
your shoulder bag and wherever you get
to you complain that that place smells
of
cuz you brought it with yourself.
And uh yeah, that's like accepting of
that even if you don't do anything else
ever in your life. Just accepting that
the value of not running away from the
confinement imposed by the precepts
restraint withdrawal. That's already a
massive step in the right direction
because again it's going to be
the mind will not be indifferent towards
it. It's it's a very strong kind of habit
It's it's a very strong kind of habit
and force. They get people to move or
avoid or compensate or manage or um
develop the views as as means of coping
with that confinement. So you have to
keep reminding yourself to stay with it
to not fuel it to not blindly follow it.
How long depends on how wild the mind
was, how wild you allow it allowed it to
be in the past.
But sooner or later it will have to sit
down. Same again similarly of the
elephant in the sutas. You you trap it
from the wilderness. I actually saw a
video of the ancient Indian technique of
taming the elephant. It was like what
the sutas describe. You get you separate
these elephant. You get them into this
enclosure of these massive posts and
stuff and they go feral. They're mental.
They're trying to break destroy like
absolute kind of rabbit panic.
>> But then they calm down.
They urinate, defecate, scream, but then
there is like the walls too strong and
then they calm down. There is no other
choice. And it's exactly what the sutas
describe. The mind is contained. When it comes
The mind is contained. When it comes
down, then the monk kind of offers the
next step of training so to speak or
like the trainer for the elephant. um
you confine it and you have to wait for
it until it sits on its own till it
comes down and then you offer it some
food. Okay, listen. As it's clear to you
now, we are not spilling out into the
old ways that you are pressuring me to
do. But if you're happy, we can do stuff
within this new perimeter. And if the
mind says, "No, get away. I'll kill
you." Then okay, you wait there longer.
And that's exactly the part of the
simile where the trainer comes and
offers some food and water to the
elephant that has come down because it
exhausted itself but it's still wild. is
like okay I'll come back later and then
comes back later eventually the elephant
will accept it and when it accepts it
it's like okay now we speak on my terms
and I think one of the the probably the
entire you know what I always sort of
have a bone to pick the commentary the
contemp contemporary views the
meditation techniques the managements
the worst thing of of why all those
things are so unbeneficial
is because they kind of enable people to
believe that they can start the training
of the mind without the prior
confinement without having the mind settle down
without having the mind settle down
after the panic existential threat
confined by the actual precepts being
trained in. not giving into the
unbeneficial behavior and then not
running away from the confinement either
until you see your mind sit down
and all these contemporary practices
enable people to believe that they can
practice without doing that although as
I said it doesn't take great kind of
study of the sutas to discover that that
is absolutely necessary that's like the
first step
and people will think yeah yeah I know I
know I'm doing it bit by bit in the
meantime the real practice is this or
that that and I'm getting closer to it.
It's like no,
>> you're just sort of believing that yeah
look the mind is listening. Yeah. Yeah.
Because the mind just happened to be
wanting to walk in the same direction
that you are going. But quickly you'll
find out that it's not in your control
when that direction changes
or when something else comes in the way
and changes it.
So then ironically enough the practice
of training the mind on account of the
right confinement uh gets swapped for
managing the mind and allowing it to
perpetually sort of uh uh uh escape the
confinement. So I don't go back to
centrality but I go back to this
technique to that teaching to this to
this move the monastery move that so
basically you as I said a person might
not have been as kind of behaving
coarsely about it because they do keep
the precepts but now everything else
they've done in the name of practice is
actually rooted in avoiding confinement
internally and that's why like they don't start
and that's why like they don't start
practicing even 50 years later
but it always remains perpetually
available Right there in your face.
>> Did you say something?
>> Oh yes. It is like running away from
suffering. And when I would like to know
what suffering is possible.
>> Well, that's what suffering that's where
suffering comes from. comes from the
from the um
chitta that has no
diminished cravings
and you don't see that presence of duka
is because of the presence of craving in
your chitta [snorts]
>> it is this raging elephant
>> yeah it might not even be that raging
Like maybe you have kept the precepts.
Maybe you don't have strong desires like
different people have different
preferences and so on.
>> But the fact is you haven't made a
connection that presence of craving
inside of the animal inside of the mind
means presence for suffering for you.
Whether you get what you want or not
becomes irrelevant. Simply the attitude
of craving in that elephant is felt as
suffering in you.
So that's why you want to train the mind
to stop craving so that you are free
from suffering.
>> But for as long as you don't see that
your suffering will be attributed to oh
because he said something or I didn't
get what I want or I got too much of
what I didn't want and so on. But those
things are indirect
causes so to speak. Not even causes.
They're indirect circumstances because
of which the animal choose to react this
way or that way. And you not see that by
not seeing that you are the one
suffering on account of it. That's why
like the prerequisite for sodapati is
seeing the animal seeing the chitta to
begin with
because that's where the craving is.
>> So you are not doing the craving you're
just inadvertently enabling it.
And that's also why you can't just stop
or just stop the craving. Just let go
and stop the craving. Just switch it
off. No, you got to confine the animal so
No, you got to confine the animal so
that it cannot proliferate that craving
further and then it needs to calm down
within that
and then you dictate as I said you know
the beneficial behavior the path
everything that you know the wholesome
thoughts not unh wholesome the right
perceptions and so on and then that
craving of that animal the urges the
compulsion the pressure become more and
more apparent and the more apparent it
is the clearer it becomes to you that
that's the root of suffering absent of
that is freedom from suffering
and the path to fulfill that is the path
of confining rightly until it sees for
itself
>> and this uh
contemplations or things it is like food
for this elephant it is calm down
>> it's yeah same like well you're familiar
with the dogs so it's like you know you
try to give a command to a dog that um
that's not giving you attention it's not
going to
So first you have to get its attention
and then give it a command and then it
responds and this is the same. So if the
mind is not confined enough has not
settle down in that confinement without
you allowing it to spill out because it
was too much because of your views took
you in the directions and ideas that you
know are rooted in compulsion.
So if the mind is not calmed down enough
you giving perception it's like shouting
at a dog that not even see you because
it's so occupied with something else.
So first you need to make it clear no no
you are here with me every the world
that you like the wilderness that you
depend on is no more and that's why I
say to people like even if you spend
next 50 years trying to keep the eight
precepts and failing every second day
but each time you take it up you take it
in an infinite sense you're actually
practicing more than somebody who keeps
them for the rest of their life but
never really takes it on mentally that
for the rest of their life they will
never engage with this. They just
circumstantially remain unengaged but
living off the pleasure of the
possibility that they could escape the
confinement if they want to. So it's
like no no it has to be infinite even if
you fail.
>> Yes. Because this is talking to any
>> because that's what exactly that's what
speaks to the mind. When you start uh uh
deciding or determining on the level of
those possibilities of escape that the
mind can find the joy in that's where
the mind get starts to listen.
But if it's just circumstantial yes no I
abstain this I don't know for how long
it's like okay so the mind still lives
off hope that well sooner or later I can
go back to those things. Yes, I know
right. >> Yeah. And it's like oh E has to be other
>> Yeah. And it's like oh E has to be other
way around. That's completely upside
down. It's like even as I said even if
you successfully manage to keep the
precepts only for like one week if when
you decided to keep it with the idea was
oh for the rest of my life mind will not
go back to this that one week can be a
lot more beneficial than as I say seven
months of just keeping the precepts
because you're in the environment when
there is nothing challenging you and not
many temptations. But never take it on
in that like mental sense like no no no
I am confining you within this new norm
of behavior.
>> If it is not indefinite it is like I'm
walking this animal I'm thinking it is
doing what I want.
>> Well yeah if it's not indefinite then
the mind is like sure sure I'll listen
to you uh until you let me out and then
we're back on to you know what I used to
do. How do you balance that with like
How do you balance that with like
realism? So maybe maybe not the precepts
but for example if you tell yourself
whenever the mind is lazy like this uh
reflection you were talking about if you
see your mind being lazy you just do the
thing that it's being lazy in regards to
>> you can kind of take that on but uh how
would you do it in the permanent sense
if you just if there's just kind of the
realistic sense of knowing that it will
take several iterations of taking it on
for it to stick
>> well
>> if you see trial and error.
>> Yeah.
>> But you shouldn't really uh you
shouldn't surrender to that like, oh,
I'll do it and then we'll see.
>> Well, no, because that already um kind
of dilutes the quality of it.
>> That's already like half half committed.
>> But it t it takes a bit more effort to
reestablish it when you know that you've
>> Exactly.
>> Yeah.
>> Exactly. Yeah. But see
through reestablishing it the level
where those determinations and decisions
and choices should be made becomes
clearer and clearer.
>> I see. Yeah. So you can find that spot
so to speak
>> quicker and quicker.
>> Yeah.
>> Or more accurately so to speak. But it
does always come down to again none of
these unbeneficial things can happen on
their own. They're always rooted in your
choice. It has to be that way.
So it's like you are the one who chooses
to release the elephant
to let [snorts] it go too far to to to
allow to cover up to pretend that it's
not confined and so on
which means you could just abstain from
that choice and maintain the practice.
You don't have to keep doing anything
new
and that's everything boils down to you
know what we often say in the talks yeah
you know you have the the broad precepts
the kind of course behavior kind of not
giving into that but then the time comes
when you recognize am I acting out of
pressure and do I feel justified in
doing So
doesn't matter what it is
like am I acting out of compulsion and
do I feel justified in doing so which
means I am giving in
to the degree that's still present in
the to the degree of wilderness that's
still present in that elephant and I'm
giving into that
so for as long as there is compulsion of
any kind craving of any kind I can't say
I'm
So have I been inadvertently maintaining
that craving through my views of what
should be done in the name of practice
while in reality I was just acting out
of compulsion and avoiding confinement
and that's where that questioning comes
in. It's like why do I need to do
anything when the pressure arises to act? Hold
when the pressure arises to act? Hold
on.
Why do I accept accept it? Why do I want
to get rid of it? Can I just not do
either and stay with it for as long as
it wants to stay? Even if I hope, oh, I
hope it goes away soon, I still choose
to stay with it and not make it go away.
Because having to do anything on account
of anything is a form of burden.
Because what if you can't do what you
what you think you're supposed to do or
what you perceive as the way out? What
if you can't do it?
So you can't then say I'm free. I'm I'm
I'm imperturbable. I'm burdenless. I'm
untouched like a lotus above the water.
If I still have to do something
means I'm not my mind is not calm enough
or trained well enough in regard to the
confinement whereby
it can sit and take it like the sutas
describe the elephant getting it ready
for the battle start being pronged with
sticks and and and spears and hit and if
it's still kind of shies pulls away
hides it trunks like oh it's not ready
it's ready when it doesn't move because
it doesn't need to
But the only way to find that out is if
you stop enabling it to move,
I think It's challenging when it starts
accumulating like with tantis and this
comes this comes and then it just kind
of goes on and then at one
[clears throat] point you're just
overwhelmed and kind of but then it's
again just
>> then you restart.
>> Yes.
>> And each time you restart rightly
um the overwhelm being overwhelmed will
be will be will be put in a in a in a
better perspective
because that's the point. It doesn't
matter how many moving parts there are,
the framework of the feeling remains the
same. So whether it's one thing that's
uncomfortable or thousand things
uncomfortable, you know that discomfort
is there.
That's the satipana correctly done.
Instead of this from left I go to right
and do that and when it's this I present
like no I know pleasant feeling is
pleasant feeling unpleasant is
unpleasant. Whichever feeling is there I
know that's what's felt.
It doesn't matter if it's big or small,
multiple, individual. Same with the
state of mind. It doesn't matter why and
how and how many times and how long. He
says he knows the mind of last as mind
of last full stop. You don't need more
information. You don't need more
specific details. Mind of anger is mind
of anger. Doesn't matter if it's a
little bit irritation or a big anger.
Mind of anger is there. Animal is angry.
I that's what I know and that's all I
need to know.
Depressed mind as depressed mind not
depressed mind but then you undepress it
through doing this and that and that.
No, knowing it for what it is is how you
basically set it up rightly.
So depressed mind is not a problem. Mind
of lust is not a problem. Mind of anger
is not a problem. You not seeing it as
such. That's where the problem is.
>> Yeah. And you don't see it cuz you keep
giving into the pressure and
compulsional tendency to just change it
this one time and then I'll stop doing.
I promise.
>> One thing I was thinking about the
feeling like that these are three types
of feelings and me not being over the
shore yet means I have craving.
>> Not being over what?
>> Over the river on the other shore.
Right. So craving is always present and
craving it's always felt unpleasantly
because it's
>> well yeah yeah
>> if if a person is honest enough to to
admit that and not just perpetually kind
of maintain the delusion.
>> Yes. So that's what what I was thinking
is then everything that it feels
pleasantly actually not like it's kind
of
>> well yes
>> twisted
>> because of this
>> well yeah because like when you get the
elephant in the enclosure or the dog
everything it wants to do is for the
sake of getting out.
So that's why there is no other way
around or or a magical solution other
than have to keep it in that setup in
that that internal confinement until it
calms down within that and accepts that
as the new environment. Then you can
allow it to move to do this or that
within that space that's not concerned
with escaping anymore.
And that's when you start to recognize
the difference between intentions that
are free from craving and intentions
that are not.
And intentions that are not are the ones
that are concerned with escape,
escaping the confinement. If the
intention is not about escaping
confinement, then it's fine. That's what
I mean. Like for as long as the dog
wants to escape, well, you keep it on a
leash. Wants to jump the jump the fence,
wants to dig under it, you keep it on a
leash. When it comes down and stops
doing that, you don't have to keep it
like next to you. You can let it go. Let
it run. let it play cuz it's not
concerned with escaping anymore.
And then sure you can refine that as
well now that further training but that
will be self-evident how to do it if you
would have overcome the general kind of
tendency of the mind to want to escape
all the way.
>> But that's the thing if I I I cannot
know pleasant feeling because I have
none. So is it
>> Well, you do. What do you mean you have
none? >> Yeah, because I have I keep having
>> Yeah, because I have I keep having
craving or
like >> Well, yes, but again craving is not the
>> Well, yes, but again craving is not the
cause of feeling.
>> Craving is in regard to feeling.
>> Yes.
>> So everything you feel gets distorted
through craving. But that doesn't mean
that you don't know what pleasure or
agreeability is.
You just don't know how to experience it
apart from craving.
And think about it again. Same simile.
You do have an animal enclosed
but still what is on its mind what is on
your mind's mind is to escape to escape
the confinement. So within that
confinement it can find agreeable things
but it won't appreciate them
because it's still concerned with more
important thing to escape because it
still has a hope of escaping because it
still thinks that you will let it out
eventually. Maybe you yourself are not
clear and so on. But when it accepts
that that there is no escape from this
confinement and it comes down then yes
oh there is that joyful thing that I
remember from before I just paid no
attention to it because again my
concerns were of a different kind
and it's you saying people can relate to
this like you know the saying oh you
don't know how good you had it until you
lose it like things you you things you
take for granted things you look past
things you think you ah this is
irrelevant I give Yeah. >> [snorts]
>> [snorts]
>> So that's what I mean there is and
that's what Buddha says like develop
pleasure of renunciation
to abandon the pleasure of
non-renunciation the pleasure of
non-confinement and spilling out into
the sense sense world same develop the
the pains of renunciation
so to replace the pains of the world the
sensuality and so on they're factually
better pains pains of renunciation so
pains that you experience on A kind of
rightly set up confinement
will make you overcome the pains of the
world. And then these pains will be
easily understood because they're not uh
manifold, overwhelming, deceiving and so
on. Because the animal is contained and
it's actually now there is a
communication between you two as opposed
to open the gate and
you hope it might come back in three
days for for a minute and generally just
run on autopilot in regard to wants,
likes, dislikes, pressures, hindrances
and stuff.